Finding Aid for David W. Osler papers, 1956-2014
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
David W. Osler papers
1956-2014
Osler, David W.
2008176 Aa 2
Ann Arbor, Michigan architect, Modern architecture, architectural drawings, presentation boards, photographs, journal articles, award submission notebooks, publicity material, and brief project summaries
1960 drawings architectural drawings
1.3 linear feet in 2 boxes textual and photographic material
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated in 2008 by David W. Osler (donor no. 10129), with additional accessions in 2009, 2012, and 2014.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
David W. Osler was born in 1921 and raised in Ann Arbor, Michigan, spending much of his childhood in the family home on Glazier Way. His early adventures in the surrounding seventeen acres of woods and creeks inspired his life-long love of the land and his sensitivity to site in architectural design. He graduated from Ann Arbor's University High School in 1938 and from the University of Michigan in 1942, where he studied design and illustration and was a member of the Big Ten Championship golf team.
During World War II, Osler enlisted in the Navy and served aboard the assault-transport ship, USS Thomas Jefferson, which deployed the first wave of American soldiers in their landing on Omaha Beach. After returning home in 1946, he married Connie Lorch, whom he had known since the ninth grade. Connie's father, Emil Lorch, was the founder of the University of Michigan Department of Architecture, dean of the School of Architecture and professor from 1906 to 1940. Osler and his wife Connie have three children, all of whom have chosen careers in design. Robin is the founding principal of the New York firm, EOA/ Elmslie Osler Architect, and Peter is the director of the Program of Landscape Architecture at the Illinois Institute of Technology. Molly, an interior designer in Ann Arbor, has often collaborated with her father in his architectural projects.
Osler's first professional job as an architect was with the firm of Douglas D. ("Pete") Loree, Architect. In 1957, Osler became a registered architect in the state of Michigan and established his own firm, David W. Osler, Architect, in the next year. He was among a number of distinguished architects who practiced in the Modern style in the Ann Arbor area in the middle and second half of the twentieth century. His earliest commissions were primarily single-family residences. However, over many decades, Osler developed a diverse portfolio of Ann Arbor projects, some of which included the Oslund Condominiums, Newport West Condominiums, St. Clare of Assisi Episcopal Church, the former Nellie Loving Branch of the Ann Arbor Library, Geddes Lakes Townhouses, and alterations and additions to the Ann Arbor District Library and National Bank and Trust Company. He is also known for his excellence in design of buildings across the state, among them, the Albion College International House and Gerstacker Language Center, the Williams Research Headquarters in Walled Lake, the Fife Electric Company Office and Warehouse in Novi, and the Harry S. Peterson Company Office Building in Orion Township. He was also responsible for the restoration of the historic Beaubien House (built in 1851) in Detroit, and the restoration/expansion of the Howell Carnegie District Library (built in 1906), for which he received the American Institute of Architects (AIA)/American Library Association Library Building Award in 1993.
During his 50-year career, Osler and his firm received many honors. In 1981, he was elected to the College of Fellows in the American Institute of Architects and was given the Michigan AIA Gold Medal Award in 1996, "for contributions to principled architectural problem-solving and for consistently high standards of design excellence." [1]
David W. Osler Associates, Inc., Architects, was honored as the Michigan AIA Firm of the Year Award in 2005. Over the decades, the firm received a total of twenty-two Michigan AIA Honor Awards, more than any other office of comparable size in the state, for such projects as the Oslund Condominiums, the Michigan Theater Restoration (with Quinn Evans), National Bank and Trust Company, the Kumasaka Residence, St. Clare of Assisi Episcopal Church, the Wilt Residence and the Nellie S. Loving Branch Library.
In 1983, Osler was honored as a finalist in the design competition for the Vietnam Veterans War Memorial in Washington, D.C. Of the 1421 competition entries, Osler's design was one of fifteen to receive honorable mention for his submission.
The architectural offices of Osler's firm were housed during his entire career in the historic, towered Washtenaw Light and Power sub-station (1902), located at 916 Fuller Street in Ann Arbor, which he purchased in a dilapidated state and renovated for his professional use in 1959. In addition to his 50 years of work as a distinguished architect, Osler has served as a University of Michigan School of Architecture adjunct professor and as a nine-year board member of the Washtenaw Metropolitan Planning Commission. Collateral activities on behalf of the architectural profession included service as the president of the local chapter of AIA, secretary of the Michigan AIA and member of the National AIA Committee on Design.
Osler retired from architectural practice in 2008. As a master of space, form, proportion, color and refinement, he leaves a legacy of design elegance and simplicity and has inspired his followers with his commitment to a high quality of community life through architecture.
---------------
1. AIA Michigan Gold Medal-1996 Citation, Box 1, David W. Osler Papers, Bentley Historical Library
The David W. Osler Papers document the professional career of this distinguished Ann Arbor architect, between the years 1956 and 2008. The collection provides researchers with a rich body of textual and visual materials, which illuminate the design excellence for which he is well known. Encompassing architectural drawings for 90 projects and photographs of 54 buildings, these papers offer a broad documentation of Osler's distinctive work in designing residences, libraries, churches, corporate and academic buildings, and condominiums. The collection contains the following series: Professional Papers, Photographs and Architectural Drawings.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Arcadia Creek (Kalamazoo, Mich.); Architects--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Kalamazoo (Mich.); Osler, David W.; War memorials--United States.; Vietnam Veterans Memorial (Washington, D.C.)
Subjects: Visual Materials
Commercial facilities--Michigan.; Condominiums--Michigan.; Libraries--Michigan.; Osler, David W.; Residences--Michigan--Detroit.; St. Clare of Assisi Episcopal Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Williams Research Corporation (Walled Lake, Mich.)
Genre Terms:
Architectural drawings.; Photographs.
- Professional Papers
  The Professional Papers series includes newspaper and journal articles about Osler and his firm from 1958 to 2012, award citations, award submission notebooks, publicity and marketing materials, and brief project summaries. Researchers will note that there are no client business files in this collection. In the Awards sub-series, the Michigan AIA Gold Medal Award (1996) folder includes letters of support from such notable Michigan architects and landscape architects as Gunnar Birkerts, Robert M. Beckley, Balthazar Korab, Charles W. Cares, S. Glen Paulsen, Robert C. Metcalf, Frederick W Mayer and Carl O. Hueter, among many. The high regard of others in Osler's profession is clearly evident in these letters, as they describe the elements of Osler's work, temperament and design, which elevate him for this award. The AIA Michigan Firm Award (2005) folder was prepared by Osler's office and combines his narrative description of seventeen chosen projects with color photographs of interiors and exteriors.
  - Newspaper and Journal Articles
    - 1958-1979 (Box 1)
    - 1980s (Box 1)
    - 1990s (Box 1)
    - 2000s (Box 1)
    - Obituary and Remembrance, 9/8/2014; 9/24/2014 (Box 1)
  - Awards
    - Michigan AIA Gold Medal, 1996 (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor Rotary Club Emeritus Status Award, 2012 (Box 1)
    - Lists of Awards and Selected Projects (Box 1)
    - American Institute of Architects Michigan, Firm Award, 2005; loose-leaf book with photographs, drawings and text, featuring seventeen projects (Map-case 6, Folder 5)
  - Award Submission Notebooks
    The Award Submission Notebooks in this first series are also of great value to researchers because they combine Osler's own descriptions with professional photographs and architectural drawings of 13 projects in spiral-bound books. Through these, one understands the program and design challenges of each building. The Project Summaries, 1965-1993, sub-series also offers this perspective, with a single-page narrative and images for twenty-nine of his projects. Within the Publicity/Marketing sub-series, the Miniature Perspective Drawings Brochure integrates Osler's art work for thirty-one projects into one tiny book. While the full-sized, original perspectives appear within the Architectural Drawings series, this brochure pulls many together in one effective piece, which highlights the architect's considerable artistic talent.
    - Ann Arbor Public Library, Ann Arbor, MI, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Auburn Hills Public Library, 1995 (Box 1)
    - Canton Public Library, Canton, MI, 2003 (Box 1)
    - Cincinnati Hillside Housing Competition, Ohio, undated (Box 1)
    - Evergreen North Elderly Housing, Oshtemo Township, MI, 1979 (Box 1)
    - Gordonwood Conference Center, Ortonville, MI, 1984 (Box 1)
    - Harry S. Peterson Company, Lake Orion, MI, 1986 (Box 1)
    - Howell Carnegie District Library, Howell, MI, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Mundus Residence, Ann Arbor, MI, 1978 (Box 1)
    - National Bank and Trust, Ann Arbor, MI, undated (Box 1)
    - Private Residence, 1969 (Box 1)
    - Private Residence, 1982 (Box 1)
    - St. Clare of Assisi Episcopal Church, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Project Summaries, 1965-1993
    - Summaries, descriptions and photographs of twenty-nine projects (Box 1)
  - Publicity/Marketing
    - Miniature Perspective Drawings Brochure, 36 photographs 2x7-1/4-inch (Box 1)
    - Firm Brochures, 1981-2003 (Box 1)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series includes black-and-white and color prints, which document the exteriors and interiors of some fifty-four of Osler's buildings. Many photographic prints are originals, and some are signed by Greg Hursley of Hursley and Lark and by Balthazar Korab, the renowned Michigan architectural photographer. When indicated on the images, dates and professional photographers are noted. The architect's career is also visually represented in two sets of foam core, accordion, exhibition panels, which combine 72 color prints of unidentified interiors and exteriors with Osler's statement about his influences, values and work.
  - Airey, Mr. John, Jr., Residence, Ann Arbor, by Hursley & Lark, 1961; 1 prints (Box 1)
  - Ann Arbor City Hall, by Balthazar Korab, 1987; 1 prints (Box 1)
  - Auburn Hills Public Library, by Balthazar Korab, undated; 11 transparencies color; 10 prints (Box 1)
  - Beaubien House, Detroit, undated; 3 prints (Box 1)
  - Berkley Public Library, by Balthazar Korab, undated; 15 transparencies color; 6 prints (Box 1)
  - Birmingham Unitarian Church, undated; 3 prints (Box 1)
  - Carroll/Virgo, Residence, Ann Arbor, undated; 18 prints (Box 1)
  - Corwin, Frederic, Residence, Jackson, MI, undated; 1 prints (Box 1)
  - David W. Osler, Architect, Office Building, undated; 1 prints (Box 1)
  - David W. Osler Associates, Architects, Exhibit, undated; 2 prints (Box 1)
  - Emmanuel Lutheran Church, undated; 1 prints (Box 1)
  - Evergreen North Housing for the Elderly, undated; 3 prints (Box 2)
    (1 print by Balthazar Korab)
  - Fife Electric, Novi, MI, undated; 4 prints (Box 1)
  - First Unitarian Universalist Church of Ann Arbor, undated; 1 prints (Box 1)
  - Gallup Park Visitor Center and Canoe Livery, Ann Arbor, undated; 7 prints (Box 1)
  - Gerstacker Language Center, Albion College, 1970; 5 prints (Box 1)
    (1 print by Hursley and Lark)
  - Gordonwood Conference Center, Ortonville, MI, 1984; 3 prints (Box 1)
  - Grosse Pointe Public Library, 1987; 1 prints (Box 1)
  - Group 243, Incorporated, Ann Arbor, 1986; 10 prints (Box 2)
  - Harry S. Peterson Company, Lake Orion, undated; 16 prints (Box 2)
  - Henrie, Arthur & Sally, Residence, Jackson, MI, undated; 14 prints (Box 1)
  - Highland Township Public Library, undated; 4 prints (Box 1)
  - Howell Carnegie District Library, 1991; 8 prints (Box 1)
  - Independence Lake Park Pavilions and Meeting Center, Washtenaw County, undated; 6 prints (Box 2)
    (1 print by Greg Hursley)
  - Kahler, Dr. & Mrs. Frank W., Residence, Ann Arbor, March 2014; 40 prints color; thumbnail prints (Box 1)
    (prints by Rapattoni Corporation)
  - Kaiser Industries, undated; 1 prints (Box 1)
  - Kalamazoo/Arcadia Creek Urban Design Plan, undated; 1 photographs (Box 1)
  - Kumasaka, Glen H., Residence, Ann Arbor, undated, 1 prints (Box 1)
  - Malcolm, Dr. Karl, Residence, Ann Arbor, undated; 3 prints (Box 1)
  - Mechanical Dynamics Office Building, undated; 2 prints (Box 1)
  - Michigan Square, Ann Arbor, by Hursley & Lark, undated; 1 prints (Box 1)
  - Michigan Theater, Ann Arbor, undated; 1 prints (Box 1)
  - Milan Senior/Community Activities Center, undated; 1 prints (Box 1)
  - Mill Creek Low-Income Housing, Ann Arbor, undated; 3 prints (Box 2)
  - Mundus Residence, Ann Arbor, undated; 2 prints (Box 2)
  - National Bank and Trust Company, Ann Arbor, 1975; 7 prints (Box 2)
    (2 prints by Balthazar Korab; 1 print by Daniel Bartush)
  - Northside Community Center, undated; 2 prints (Box 1)
  - Osler, David, undated; 2 portrait prints black and white; 1 transparencies (Box 1)
  - Oslund Condominiums, Ann Arbor, undated; 2 transparencies by Balthazar Korab; 11 prints by unknown photographer (Box 1)
  - Planned Parenthood of Michigan, Ann Arbor, undated; 4 prints (Box 1)
  - Riverview City Hall Council Chamber, undated; 1 prints (Box 1)
  - Selected Projects of David W. Osler & Partners, Inc., undated (Box 1)
    (Includes David W. Osler, Architect, Office; Nellie S. Loving Branch Library; Conlin Travel Bureau; Gilkey Residence; St. Clare of Assisi Episcopal Church; Sigma Phi Fraternity House; Rapp Residence; Racquet Club Swim Building; and Geddes Lakes Townhouses, etc.)
  - St. Clare of Assisi Episcopal Church, Ann Arbor, undated; 13 prints; 2 transparencies (Box 1)
  - Unidentified Exteriors, undated; 8 prints (Box 2)
    (2 prints by Balthazar Korab; 4 prints by Greg Hursley)
  - Unidentified Interiors, undated; 10 prints (Box 2)
  - University of Michigan Women's Soccer and Field Hockey Facilities, undated; 1 prints (Box 1)
  - University of Michigan Tennis Center, Ann Arbor, undated; 1 prints (Box 1)
  - Washtenaw County 14th District Court House, Ypsilanti, MI, undated; 1 prints (Box 1)
  - Williams Research Corporation, 1974; 10 prints (Box 2)
  - Exhibition Panel I, undated; 7 accordion panels on foam core, with thirty-six color prints of unidentified interiors and exteriors and architect's statement (Panel 1)
  - Exhibition Panel II, undated; 6 accordion panels on foam core, with thirty-six color prints of unidentified interiors and exteriors (Panel 2)
- Architectural Drawings
  The Architectural Drawings series reflects the diverse design portfolio of David Osler over the five decades of his career, including 1947 perspective, preliminary design and construction drawings for 90 private residences, churches, libraries, office and academic buildings and park facilities. The earliest project, a residence in Barton Hills, Ann Arbor, for Jack Dobson (1956), is documented with original, pencil-on-vellum, construction drawings, as are many of the buildings in the collection. For a number of projects, such as the Cincinnati Hillside Housing Competition, Emmanuel Lutheran Church in Livonia, the Fife Electric Company Office and Warehouse in Novi, and the Hoffman Building in Ann Arbor, only a few perspective drawings are available. However, these beautiful, hand-drawn perspectives illuminate Osler's outstanding artistic skills.
  The projects in this series are listed alphabetically and not chronologically. However, it is evident that, during the 1960s, Osler concentrated on designing single-family residences for friends and clients who had purchased lots in new subdivisions in the Ann Arbor area. By the second decade of his career, the architect was tackling larger commissions, such as Newport West Condominiums and the renovation of National Bank and Trust Company in Ann Arbor. For many of these large projects, full sets of preliminary and construction drawings are included, documenting the entire, sometimes lengthy, design process. The Oslund Condominiums project is represented by twelve folders of drawings, from 1968 through 2003. Other buildings with a large number of design and construction drawings are the Howell Carnegie District Library, the Auburn Hills Public Library, the Brandon Township Public Library in Ortonville, and the Nellie S. Loving Branch Library in Ann Arbor.
  Of particular interest to researchers wishing to exhibit Osler's work are the large 36x48-inch Presentation Boards on poster board and tempered masonite for two of his projects. The Kalamazoo/Arcadia Creek Urban Design and Development Plan has four presentation boards, showing two site plans and twelve perspectives. The Vietnam War Veterans Memorial Competition has two presentation boards, which include perspectives, site plans, and elevation and section drawings. These boards are of particular significance because Osler was honored as a finalist in this nation-wide competition in 1983.
  - Airey, John, Jr., Residence, Hunting Valley Road, Ann Arbor, Michigan (1961)
    - Construction Drawings by David W. Osler, Architect, 10/15/1961; 14 drawings architectural, structural and electrical drawings; pencil-on-vellum originals (Map-case 1, Folder 1)
  - Albion College International House and Gerstacker Language Center, Albion, Michigan (1967-1970)
    - Preliminary Drawings by David W. Osler, one dated, 1/21/1967; 6 drawings perspectives; 1 drawings architectural drawing; pencil-on-vellum originals (Map-case 1, Folder 2)
    - Construction Drawings by David W. Osler, Architect, 3/12/1969-7/10/1979; 38 drawings architectural, structural and landscape drawings; pencil-on-vellum originals (Map-case 1, Folder 2)
  - Ann Arbor Country Club Pool House, Webster Township, Washtenaw County, Michigan (1964)
    - Construction Drawings by David W. Osler, Architect 1/30/1964 revised 4/16/1964, 11 drawings architectural and mechanical/electrical drawings; pencil-on-vellum originals (Map-case 1, Folder 1)
  - Ann Arbor District Library Addition, Fifth Avenue and Williams Street, Ann Arbor, Michigan (1991)
    - Preliminary Drawings, undated; 2 blueprints colored pencil drawings on blue-line prints (Map-case 1, Folder 3)
  - Arpaci, Professor and Mrs. Vedat, Residence, Penberton Drive, Ann Arbor, Michigan (1969-1986)
    - Construction Drawings by David W. Osler, Architect, 1/15/1969; 14 drawings architectural, mechanical and electrical drawings; pencil-on-vellum originals (Map-case 1, Folder 4)
    - Design Development Drawings of Conversation Area by David Osler, Architect (, 3/27/1970; 2 drawings architectural drawings; pencil-on-vellum originals (Map-case 1, Folder 4)
    - Remodeling Construction Drawings by Osler Milling Architects, Inc. &, 1975; 7/10/1986; 3 drawings architectural drawings; pencil-on-mylar and on-vellum originals (Map-case 1, Folder 4)
  - Auburn Hills Public Library Renovation and Expansion Building, Civic Center Complex, East Seyburn Drive, Auburn Hills, Michigan (1994-1995)
    - Construction Drawings (Map-case 1, Folder 5)
      - Architectural and Landscape Drawings (T-1 to A-12) by David W. Osler Associates, Inc., Architects, 8/25/1994-3/28/1995; 16 drawings red pencil drawings on mylar prints (Map-case 1, Folder 5)
      - Architectural Drawings (A-13 to A-29), 3/28/1995-5/31/1995; 17 drawings mylar prints (Map-case 1, Folder 6)
      - Mechanical and Electrical Drawings by David W. Osler Associates, Inc., Architects, and S. F. Sonk Associates, Inc., 3/28/1995; 19 drawings electrostatic prints on vellum and mylar (Map-case 1, Folder 7)
  - Beaubien House Restoration (Charles Trombley House and Michigan Architectural Foundation), 553 East Jefferson Avenue, Detroit, Michigan (built 1851)
    - Construction Drawing (A-2) by Osler Milling Architects, Inc., 11/29/1983; 1 drawings pencil-on-vellum (Map-case 1, Folder 3)
  - Beck, Professor and Mrs. Charles B., Residence, Daleview Drive, Scio Township, Michigan (1965)
    - Construction Drawings by David W. Osler, Architect, 3/26/1965; 12 drawings architectural and electrical drawings; pencil-on-vellum originals (Map-case 1, Folder 8)
  - Berkley Public Library Renovation and Addition, Twelve Mile Road, Berkley, Michigan (1996-1997)
    - Schematic Design and Construction Drawings by David W. Osler Associates, Inc., Architects, Structural Design, Inc., and S. F. Sonk Associates, 12/2/1996-9/2/1997; 40 drawings architectural, structural and mechanical, electrical;plumbing drawings; pencil-on-vellum originals, prints on mylar and vellum, and CAD drawings on vellum (Map-case 1, Folder 9)
  - Bohlen, Robert, Residence, Fowlerville, Michigan
    - Schematic Design Drawings by Osler/Milling Architects, Inc., undated; 2 drawings architectural drawings; pencil-on-vellum originals (Map-case 1, Folder 3)
  - Brandon Township Public Library, South Street, Ortonville, Michigan (1999-2001)
    - Construction Drawings (Map-case 1, Folder 10)
      - Site Preparation and Landscape Drawings by URS Greiner Woodward Clyde, Civil Engineers, and David W. Osler Associates, Inc., Architects, 8/2/1999; 5/19/1999; 10 drawings CAD drawings on vellum (Map-case 1, Folder 10)
      - Architectural Drawings by David W. Osler Associates, Inc., Architects, 2/8/1999-2/13/2001; 206 drawings pencil originals on tracing paper and vellum and CAD drawings on vellum (Map-case 1, Folder 11)
      - Mechanical and Electrical Drawings by James Partridge Associates, Inc., 5/10/1999-8/30/1999; 10 drawings CAD drawings on vellum (Map-case 1, Folder 10)
  - Brunette, Dr. and Mrs. L., Residence, Edgemore Avenue, Kalamazoo, Michigan (1980-1981)
    - Construction Drawings by Osler Milling Architects, Inc., 3/7/1980-2/16/1981; 26 drawings architectural, structural and mechanical;electrical drawings; pencil-on-vellum originals (Map-case 1, Folder 12)
  - Byosiere, Philippe, and Impeus, Ann, Apartments, Fifth Street, Ann Arbor, Michigan
    - Schematic Design Drawings by David W. Osler Associates, Inc., Architects, undated; 35 drawings architectural drawings; pencil and ink drawings on tracing paper and vellum and on blue-line and electrostatic prints (Map-case 1, Folder 13)
  - Carroll/Virgo Residence, Geddes Road, Ann Arbor, Michigan (1980-1981)
    - Preliminary Drawings by Osler Milling Architects, Inc., 7/30/1980; 5 drawings architectural drawings; pencil-on-vellum originals (Map-case 2, Folder 1)
    - Construction Drawings by Osler Milling Architects, Inc., 9/30/1980-7/20/1981; 26 drawings architectural, mechanical and electrical drawings; pencil originals on vellum and mylar (Map-case 2, Folder 1)
  - Cincinnati Hillside Housing Competition, Cincinnati, Ohio (undated)
    - Presentation Drawing, undated; 1 drawings perspective; pencil-on-vellum original (Map-case 1, Folder 3)
  - Conlin, William J., Building Additions and Alterations, Huron Street, Ann Arbor, Michigan (1962)